<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Honey out of the rock, or, Gods method in giving the sweetest comforts in sharpest combates. Chiefly intended, as spirituall plunder for plundered beleevers.</title>
            <author>Price, John, Citizen of London.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 99 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90965</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3343</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E46_14</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R22911</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99871859</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99871859</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154500</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90965)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154500)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 8:E46[14])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Honey out of the rock, or, Gods method in giving the sweetest comforts in sharpest combates. Chiefly intended, as spirituall plunder for plundered beleevers.</title>
                  <author>Price, John, Citizen of London.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 33, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Francis Neile for Henry Overton in Popes-Head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: J.P., i.e. John Price.</note>
                  <note>With a preliminary license to print.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 10th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Persecution --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:154500:1"/>
            <p>I Have peruſed this Diſcourſe, entituled, <hi>Honey out of the Rock,</hi> and find it (anſwerable to the Title) full both of ſtrength and ſweetneſſe, and therefore do approve the publiſhing of it in Print.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>April 19. 1644.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Joſeph Caryl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154500:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>HONEY OUT OF THE ROCK, <hi>OR,</hi> GODS METHOD IN GIVING THE SWEETEST Comforts in ſharpeſt Combates.</p>
            <p>Chiefly intended, As Spirituall Plunder for Plundered Beleevers.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Judges 14.14.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Out of the eater came forth meat.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hebr. 10.34.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And took joyfully the ſpoiling of your goods, knowing in your ſelves that ye have in heaven a better and an enduring ſubſtance.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>Francis Neile</hi> for <hi>Henry Overton</hi> in Popes-Head Alley. 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:154500:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154500:2"/>
            <head>TO ALL THE PERSECVTED Members of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> eſpecially the Exiles, and Plundered, of <hi>Briſtol, Exeter, Weſtcheſter, Oxford,</hi> and elſewhere in theſe bleeding Kingdoms of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right precious in the Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is hard to ſay whether would firſt have devoured the perſecuted Saints in the Primitive times; either the depth of their miſerie, or the weight of their glorie; had not the Almightie enlarged their capacity to bear the one as well as the other, and therefore (not doubting the Father of mercies continued diſpenſations towards you (afflicted for his ſake) in a way of like abounding conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons) your poore brethren (not yet honoured as your ſelves to ſuffer for Chriſt) do look upon you, they know not whether, with more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, or holy emulation, tis true, your outward condition hath a ſad aſpect to the eye of reaſon, you are driven from the creature; but it is to the Creator, from the lower to the upper ſprings, from the ſtreame to the fountain, is this miſerie? before your troubles, you had your ordinarie commons with your fellow-beleevers, but now, your daily food is choice morſels, your ordinarie liquids; wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of life, and ſuperlative refections (<hi>Benjamins</hi> meſſe) your daily ſhare, the love of God, the power of Chriſt, the Spirit of glorie, the care of Angels, the prayers of Saints are all upon the wing for your preſent welfare, is this miſerie? the <hi>Summum bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:154500:3"/>(the great inquirie of this blind world ſearching for it in all aboundancie of outward glorie) is found by you; and you by it ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in ſackcloth and aſhes; is this miſerie, your earth is diſſolved before your bodies, and your heaven prevents you before your time, your joyes are immediate, you reap without ſowing? you feed on the kernels and break not the ſhels, you rest from your labours, the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of God, the blood of Chriſt, the joy of the ſpirit, the food of Angels, are not theſe your daily repaſt? is this miſerie? deareſt brethren, it is my ambition to be your unworthy ſervitor in your preſent ſupports, whereby, if I can but help on your joy, and inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuate my ſelf among the number of your benefactors and ſhare with them in your daily requeſts at the throne of grace, it will be a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reward unto him who is (unworthy to be mentioned with the meaneſt of you all)</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. P.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb facs="tcp:154500:3"/>
            <head>Hony out of the Rock.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Olineſſe is the object of mans hatred and Gods love, and in what ſubject ſoever it be found, it produceth the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary effects of love and hatred from God and man: there is not one thing wherein wretched man more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends with his maker, then about the peace and trouble, joy and ſorrow, life and death of the Saints of God, this the Apoſtle ſpeaks of, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8, 9. <hi>We are troubled on every ſide, but not diſtreſſed, perplexed but not in deſpair, perſecuted but not forſaken, caſt down but not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed.</hi> And Chriſt expreſly affirmeth, that <hi>in the world they ſhould have trouble, but in him, peace.</hi> Joh. 16.33. The great contention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Michael</hi> and the Devil is not now about the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as of old, <hi>Jude</hi> verſ. 9. but the body of Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> his Church, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.6. whoſe habitation though it be <hi>in the wilderneſſe, and mountains of Lebanon, and Amana, Shenir and Hermon, the Lions dens, and mountains of the Leopards.</hi> Song 4.8. yet even there is ſhe <hi>leaning upon her beloved:</hi> Chap. 8.5. and there hath God prepared a place for her where ſhe is fed and ſupported, <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.16. where <hi>he maketh peace her borders, and filleth her with the fineſt of the wheat.</hi> Pſal. 147.14. and <hi>with honey out of the rock.</hi> Pſal. 81.16. Extracts of ſpirits are moſt vigorous, how much more the Spirit of ſpirits? which is a beleevers recoverie in fainting fits, and therefore the ſubject matter of our preſent diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe ſhall be this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Spirit of Chriſt is unto beleevers the ſweeteſt comforts in their ſharpeſt combates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which Propoſition, two things are conſiderable. Firſt, that <hi>God hath given unto his Saints the Spirit of his Son.</hi> Secondly, <hi>that this Spirit yeelds forth the ſweeteſt comforts in the ſharpeſt trials.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oynt confirmation, proſecution and application whereof ſhall be endeavoured in the ſolution of theſe Queſtions.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:154500:4"/>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, why God gives unto his people the Spirit of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>Secondly, how the Spirit of Chriſt doth comfort beleevers in evill times.</item>
               <item>Thirdly, how the Spirit of Chriſt may be diſcerned from the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of deluſion</item>
            </list>
            <p>Firſt, why God gives unto his people the Spirit of his Son.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, God gives the Spirit of his Son unto Beleevers, <hi>that ſo they may be made like unto his Son.</hi> Chriſt is the expreſſe image of God, and the Saints are the expreſſe image of Chriſt, if you will know what God is, ſtudy Chriſt, there you may read his infinite juſtice, mercy, love, truth, and goodneſſe, if you will know what Chriſt was here in the world, ſtudy the Saints, <hi>viz. Quatenus,</hi> Saints, there you may read the holineſſe, meekneſſe, humilitie, patience, love, gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, with the like glorious perfection of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.7. God is ſaid to <hi>anoint Chriſt with the oyle of gladneſſe above his fellows.</hi> This is ſpoken of the Spirit, which in many places of Scripture is compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to oyle, 1. <hi>John</hi> 2.27. and elſe-where, and the anointing oyle under the Law conſiſting of many ſweet ſpices, <hi>Exodus</hi> 35.8. did tipi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the powring out of the Spirit under the Goſpel, conſiſting of many ſweet and precious graces and fruits therof, and this is called <hi>the oyle of gladneſſe</hi> to denote the chearing property of the Spirit of Chriſt, which is as ointment, <hi>Pro.</hi> 27.8. <hi>to rejoyce the heart,</hi> and with this was Chriſt <hi>anointed above his fellows,</hi> that is in reſpect of meaſure, 3. <hi>John</hi> 34. but not in reſpect of kinde, the Saints having received it <hi>of his fulnes,</hi> Joh. 1.16. <hi>it pleaſed the Father that in him all fulneſſe ſhould dwell,</hi> 1. <hi>Col.</hi> 19. but yet that this fulneſſe powred forth upon the head ſhould reach even <hi>unto the skirts of his garments,</hi> Pſal. 133.2. the Saints are called Chriſts <hi>fellows,</hi> God hath given them fellowſhip with Chriſt in the ſame inheritance, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.17. and therefore in the ſame Spirit <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. Gods deſigne was to make his Elect like his Son, and in him like him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, <hi>we ſhall be like unto Chriſt in glory,</hi> John 3.2. and we muſt be made like him in grace, even <hi>pure as he is pure,</hi> verſe 3. the Spirit of Chriſt ſtamps the image of his Son upon us, looking upon and <hi>beholding the glory of the Lord we are changed into the ſame image from glory to glory, even as by the Spirit of the Lord,</hi> 2. Cor. 3.18. that is, the firſt reaſon, God gives the Spirit of his Sonn to conforme us to the ſimilitude of his Sonne.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God gives his people the Spirit of his Son which is the fruit of his death and interceſſion, <hi>that we may be fully convinced of all
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154500:4"/>the glorious perfections and fruits of the death and merits of Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> God hath convinced us of the perfection of his love by ſending his Sonne into the world, <hi>John</hi> 3.16. <hi>God ſo loved the world, that he gave his Sonne,</hi> if you will meaſure his love, meaſure the gift, but both the one and the other is infinite; Chriſt was the enſuring earneſt of his love, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given him, he will ſurely <hi>give all things with him. Rom.</hi> 8.32.</p>
            <p>Now as Chriſt is an aſſuring teſtimonie of the perfection of Gods love, ſo the gift of the Spirit is an aſſuring teſtimonie of the perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chriſts merits, and therefore it is called <hi>the earneſt of our inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritance, untill the redemption of the purchaſed poſſeſſion,</hi> 1. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 14. greater is Chriſt then all other fruits of Gods love, and greater is the Spirit, then all other fruits of Chriſts merits: as all the fruits of Gods love are intayled unto the perſon of Chriſt; ſo all the fruits of Chriſts death are intayled unto the Spirit of Chriſt: hee that hath Chriſt need not queſtion whether God will give any other fruit of his love: ſo he that hath the Spirit, need not queſtion any other fruit of Chriſts merits; his Juſtification, Sanctification, Adoption, Grace, and Glory will follow. God would not have us doubt of his love, and therefore he hath given us the perſon of his Son; neither would he have us doubt of the fruit of Chriſts merits, aad therefore hath hee given us the Spirit of his Son, the very gift of Chriſt being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood doth convince of the love of God; and yet Chriſt in his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon did alſo preach the love of God; ſo the very gift of the Spirit doth convince of the merits of Chriſt, and yet this Spirit doth preach and declare the perfection of Chriſts merits. None in the world could be convinced of the love of God, except Chriſt had preached it unto him; ſo none in the world can be convinced of the merits of Chriſt, except this Spirit doth ſhew it and preach it unto him. Chriſt did bear witneſſe of the truth of Gods love, and <hi>his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is true, John</hi> 5.31. and it is the Spirit that beareth witneſſe unto Chriſts blood, and <hi>this Spirit is truth,</hi> 1. <hi>John</hi> 5.6. What ever God gives, and not his Son, there is no teſtimonie of Gods love; ſo what ever the ſoule hath and not the Spirit, there is no conviction of the merits of Chriſt, though the Word ſpeakes peace, and the Prophets of God ſpeakes peace, and all the people of God ſpeakes peace: yet the ſoule cannot heare it except God, <hi>viz.</hi> by his Spirit <hi>cauſe it to heare the voyce of joy and gladneſſe,</hi> Pſal. 51.8.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, God gives the Spirit of his Son unto his Saints <hi>to fit them for glory,</hi> God doth not love diſproportion: when he made a woman
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:154500:5"/>for man, hee made her <hi>a meet help,</hi> 1. Geneſis 18. When God ſent Chriſt for the worke of Redemption, he fitted him. <hi>A body haſt thou prepared</hi> or fitted, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.5. So God intending his Elect for glorie, <hi>he makes them meet to be partakers of the inheritance of the Saints in light,</hi> 1. Col. 12. <hi>and to ſit together in heavenly places in Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> 2. Epheſ. 6. and this meetneſſe is by the Spirit: for the Elect of God are <hi>choſen to ſalvation through the ſanctification of the Spirit, and beleefe of the Truth,</hi> 2. Theſſ. 2.13. who living in the Spirit, and walking in the Spirit, <hi>wait through the Spirit for the righteouſneſſe of Faith, viz.</hi> the end thereof which is the ſalvation of their ſoules, <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.5. <hi>no uncleane thing ſhall enter into the Kingdome of God,</hi> Revel. 22.15. but the Saints ſhall, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore are they <hi>waſhed, and ſanctified, and juſt fied in the Name of the Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and by the Spirit of ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God,</hi> 1. Cor. 6.11. The Sacrifices and all the appurtenances thereof under the Law were to be ſanctified and ſet apart, and the Prieſts that were to enter into the holy place were ſanctified and choſen from the world for that purpoſe; and this ſanctification was tipified by the anointing oil ſprinkled upon <hi>Aaron, Exod.</hi> 29.21. So the Saints of God are ſanctified, choſen, or ſeparated out of the world, being made ſpirituall Kings and Prieſts unto God, and appointed to come into that holy place, even the place of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie wherein dwelleth righteouſneſſe, to give <hi>glory and honour and thanks to him that ſitteth upon the Throne that liveth for ever and ever.</hi> Revel. 4.9. which ſanctification conſiſteth in the powring forth of the Spirit compared to oyle, 1. <hi>John</hi> 2.27. upon the Saints, and thereby fitting them for glory.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, God gives his people the Spirit of his Son, <hi>that ſo they may be enabled to doe and ſuffer his will in an acceptable manner,</hi> God is a Spirit, and will be worſhipped in Spirit, 4. <hi>John</hi> 23. hee requireth that wee ſhould <hi>pray in the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>ſing in the Spirit,</hi> 1. Cor. 14.15. that wee ſhould <hi>walke in the Spirit,</hi> and <hi>live in the Spirit,</hi> Gal. 5.25. that wee ſhould doe every thing from a ſpirituall principle, according to a ſpirituall rule with reference unto a ſpirituall end. God is not a hard Maſter requiring to reap where he did not ſow, exacting a tale of bricke and give no ſtraw; but that they may doe the will of God in an acceptable manner, he gives his Spirit unto all his Saints: the Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>through Chriſt we have acceſſe by one Spirit unto the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> 2. Epheſ. 18. <hi>through Chriſt, viz.</hi> the blood of Chriſt wee are brought into this grace, and by the Spirit wee are enabled to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove this grace, <hi>viz.</hi> in all ſpirituall ſervices, ſo that God gives
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154500:5"/>them his Spirit that ſo they may be enabled <hi>to offer up ſpirituall ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices acceptable unto God by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> 1. Pet. 2.5. And ſo likewiſe for paſſive obedience, he hath given them his Spirit, that with comfort and ſpirituall joy and conſolation they may undergoe that hard worke of bearing the croſſe, which leadeth me to the ſolution of the ſecond generall Queſtion: Namely, how the Spirit doth comfort be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers in evill times.</p>
            <p>How doth the Spirit of Chriſt ſupport Beleevers in evill times?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, <hi>by his owne naturall genuine and proper ſtrength and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> 1. John 4 4. <hi>You are of God little children, and have overcome the world, becauſe greater is he that is in you then he that is in the world:</hi> the Saints of God are as <hi>little children</hi> in meekneſſe, humilitie, ſingleneſſe of heart, ſimplicitie of mind, freedom from envie, dependance up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God; and though <hi>little children,</hi> yet able to grapple with, and <hi>overcome the whole world,</hi> how ſo? becauſe <hi>they are of God, (viz.)</hi> of his antient love, and the birth of his Goſpel.</p>
            <p>Secondly, becauſe God is in them, <hi>(viz.)</hi> by his Spirit, and <hi>greater is he that is in them (viz.)</hi> to ſupport, to comfort, to incourage, to preſerve, <hi>then he, (viz.)</hi> Satan, <hi>the prince of the power of the aire, the ſpirit that now worketh in the children of diſobedience,</hi> Epheſ. 2.2. <hi>that is in the world, (viz.)</hi> carnall and wicked men, to caſt down, to grieve, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage, to deſtroy. We have another Scripture for this in the third to the <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.16. <hi>I how my knee to the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that he would grant you according to the riches of his glory to be ſtrengthened with might by his Spirit in the inner man,</hi> this our God grants unto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, firſt, becauſe <hi>he is the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and in him their Father, and ſo interreſſed in the ſame power by which he was <hi>ſtrengthened in the inner man,</hi> in the daies of his fleſh, and ſufferings upon earth. Secondly, becauſe it is <hi>according to</hi> (or falling in with) <hi>the riches of his glory, (viz.)</hi> the glory of his grace by which he hath the revenews of his glorie coming in even <hi>in the higheſt</hi> degree, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.14. and whereof there are riches, even <hi>treaſures wherein he hath a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded towards them:</hi> Epheſ. 1.8. Thirdly, becauſe this is the joynt requeſt of all the Saints in each others behalf, <hi>I, viz. Paul, how my knee, viz.</hi> in prayer, <hi>unto the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that he would grant you, &amp;c.</hi> the perſon of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt intercedes in heaven for all his Saints, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 7.25. and the Spirit of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tercedes in the earth for the ſame Saints, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.27. and <hi>the Father heareth him</hi> (who did his will) interceding both by his blood and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154500:6"/>Spirit in heaven and earth. <hi>Joh.</hi> 9.31. this is that <hi>divine nature,</hi> 2 Pet. 1.4. and that <hi>power of God,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.5. whereby the Saints are kept againſt all their diſcouragements even <hi>unto ſalvation:</hi> this is that whereby the Saints <hi>are comforted in all their tribulation,</hi> 2 Cor. 1.4. and whereby their <hi>conſolations do abound</hi> in them beyond the abounding of their afflictions, verſ. 5. it is the Spirit of comfort <hi>called the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter,</hi> Joh. 14.16. which ſhall be as a continuall ſtreame or waters of life in the bowels of the Saints, to refreſh and chear them in all their loſſes and troubles of this life, the comforts whereof the Spouſe of Chriſt prayeth for, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Stay me with flaggons, and comfort me with apples, for I am ſick of love:</hi> all the troubles, ſorrows and afflictions of the Saints are ſickneſſes of love, as they are from God, they proceed from love, are ſteered by love, love is the root, and rule, and end of all: as they proceed from man, they are becauſe of their love to God, therefore in all their afflictions they may be ſaid to be ſick of love. What is her prayer? why <hi>ſtay me with thy flagons, and comfort me with thy apples,</hi> with <hi>thy flagons, viz.</hi> of wine, which <hi>cheareth the heart,</hi> Prov. 31.6. <hi>Comfort me with thy apples, viz.</hi> the glorious fruits of Jeſus Chriſt the tree of life, <hi>under whoſe ſhadow the Saints do ſit with great delight,</hi> and <hi>whoſe fruit is pleaſant unto their taſte:</hi> verſ. 2. what are all theſe expreſſions but the ſetting forth of thoſe ſweet Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt ſupporting their hearts in evill times. This is that whereof the Church reports, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.6. <hi>His left hand is under my head, and his right hand doth embrace me.</hi> See here the Churches poſture in the time of her trouble is lying in the boſome of her beloved; graſping her like a tender husband between his arms, Jeſus Chriſt hath boſome conſolations for his ſick Saints, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens of life for fainting fits, Manna is reſerved for the wilderneſſe, and the beſt wine when all is ſpent; when all forſake, the Lord ſtands by: he is <hi>light in darbueſſe,</hi> Pſal. 112.4. Act. 12.7. and mans caſting into dungeons, is but Chriſt bringing into his banqueting houſe, where his banner over them is love, <hi>his left hand is under them, and his right handimbraceth them.</hi> Chriſt hath left hand mercies, <hi>viz.</hi> the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts of this lift which though they be contracted within a ſmall bulk, even into <hi>a little oyl in a cruce,</hi> 2 King. 4.2. <hi>five barley leaves and two fiſhes</hi> for five thouſand, Joh. 6.9. that is a poore ſomething next to nothing to ſupport and maintain a great charge, why this is Chriſts left hand, and yet this ſhall be ſufficient, if he puts but the effecacie of even his left hand it ſhall be enough: but his right hand
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154500:6"/>mercies are moſt high and ſpirituall; and when the Lord doth any thing with his <hi>right hand</hi> he doth it moſt dextereouſly even unto per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as appears if you look <hi>Pſal.</hi> 60.5. <hi>That thy beloved may be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered ſave with thy right hand.</hi> And ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 20.6. 45.4. &amp;c. So when God imbraceth or comforteth with <hi>his right hand,</hi> he doth it ſo as none can diſcourage: when all ſecondarie means of comfort are gone, the Lord Jeſus doth then comfort moſt immediately, and therefore moſt perfectly: for whatſoever God doth without ſecondary cauſes alwayes are without imperfection. When he made all things at firſt coming immediately from between his hands, behold all were very good, ſo it is in his immediate conſolations: Hence it is we read of <hi>joy unſpeakable and glorious,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.8. even in the time <hi>of heavineſſe through many temptations,</hi> verſ. 6. thus Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> by his Spirit, becomes <hi>a hiding place from the wind, and a refuge from the tempeſt, as ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of water in a dry place, and the ſhadow of a great rock in a wearie land:</hi> Iſa. 32.2. Jeſus Chriſt is a ſutable good unto all his people, and what he is he makes good unto his people by his Spirit. So that as <hi>Eliiah</hi> ſtretched himſelf upon the dead child, 1 King. 17.21. and <hi>the ſoul of the child came unto him again, and he revived:</hi> ſo when the Saints are as it were kill'd and ſlain at the firſt encounter with troubles and perſecutions, and loſſes of all their comforts, why then doth the Lord Jeſus Chriſt by his Spirit as it were ſtretch forth himſelf over them, and then their life, and joy, and peace returns again, yea like unto that of the reſurrection after death in that perfection, that the weak fleſh is ſcarce able to bear it, Comforts indeed ſutable unto glorified Saints. Thus the Spirit chears and comforts the hearts of the Saints by his naturall, genuine, and proper ſtrength and influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, the Spirit of God being in it ſelf a Spirit of comfort.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Spirit chears the hearts of beleevers in evill times, <hi>by preſenting God in Jeſus Chriſt as a deare and loving Father unto them,</hi> a moſt ſweet and glorious viſion, and aſſurance whereof (for the moſt part) he vouchſafeth unto them in the dayes of their trouble. When Jeſus Chriſt was to leave the world (whoſe abſence was the ſorrow of the hearts of his Diſciples: <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.1.) he comforts them by tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, that he was going to his Father and their Father, to his God and their God. And <hi>Philip</hi> lookt upon this as a ſufficient means to ſtay the heart, <hi>Lord,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>ſhew us the Father and it ſufficeth:</hi> ver. 8. it cannot ſuffice that God is a Father, except he be a revealed Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>ſhew us the Father.</hi> And as no man cometh unto the Father but
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154500:7"/>by Chriſt, ſo no man hath ſeen the Father but the Son, and he unto whom he will reveal him. Therefore, ſaith he, <hi>Lord, ſhew us the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and this he doth by the witneſſe of his Spirit, <hi>Rom</hi> 8.16. <hi>The Spirit it ſelf beareth witneſſe with our ſpirits that we are the ſons of God,</hi> and this he doth chiefly in a ſuffering condition, for ſo the next verſe ſheweth, <hi>If ſo be we ſuffer with him, we ſhall alſo be glorified with him.</hi> The bowels of parents yearn towards their ſick children, and the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt language and moſt tender expreſſions of their affections are then little enough: <hi>Luke</hi> 15. The Prodigall had more ſerious thoughts of his father when all was gone, then it ſeems he had when he firſt received his portion: and ſo the Saints have the ſweeteſt thoughts of their heavenly Father in the ſaddeſt times. When <hi>Abraham</hi> had bound <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and was readie to ſlay him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 22. yet the child could look him in the face and cry out, <hi>my father,</hi> ver. 7. And his father could as tenderly and with as yearning bowels as ever he ſpake with all in all his life reply, <hi>Here am I my ſon:</hi> v. 8. So when the Saints of God ſeems as it were to be bound to be ſacrificed unto the good will of God in ſuffering, yet they can look in the face of God, and cry out Father, and hear the voice of God by his Spirit anſwering, here am I my children. The Spirit of God worketh a threefold con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction in the hearts of his people in the times of their ſuffering from this dear and ſweet relation.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>that he will correct in meaſure. Jer.</hi> 30.11. <hi>What ever I do,</hi> ſaith God, <hi>to other Nations, I will not make a full end of thee, but I will correct thee in meaſure,</hi> the Lord poureth forth his furie upon the heathen, <hi>but corrects his people in judgement and not in anger.</hi> Jer. 10.24, 25. he cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects in meaſure in reſpect of the matter of the afflictions, he will viſit the tranſgreſſions of his people <hi>with the rod</hi> of a father, <hi>and their iniquity with ſtripes.</hi> Pſal. 89.32. but <hi>he will break the wicked with a rod of iron, and daſh them in pieces like a potters veſſell.</hi> Pſal. 2.9. Secondly, he corrects in meaſure <hi>in reſpect of time, O my people that dwelleſt in Sion</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>be not afraid of the Aſſyrian, he ſhall ſmite thee with a rod, and ſhall lift up his ſtaffe againſt thee after the manner of Egypt, for yet a little while and the indignation ſhall ceaſe, and mine anger even in their deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: viz.</hi> of the Aſſyrian. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 10.24.25. <hi>Heavineſſe may endure for a night, but joy ſhall come in the morning.</hi> Pſal. 30.5. His anger endureth but for a moment, in his favour is life, even in the perfection both of hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe and duration, the Spirit of God convinceth the ſoul, that <hi>yet but a little while, he that ſhall come will come, and will not carrie.</hi> Hebr.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154500:7"/>10.37. that what God doth in afflicting, he will do it in meaſure, that <hi>God is faithfull, who will not ſuffer his to be tempted above what they are able to bear</hi> (that is, in reſpect of the matter of their ſuffering) <hi>but will with the temptation make a way to eſcape:</hi> there is meaſure of time. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Spirit convinceth <hi>that God as a Father doth afflict them in love, not in paſſion,</hi> for their good; not ſimply his owne will, the Apoſtle calls for ſubmiſſion unto the will of God in chaſtiſing us from that conſideration, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.9.10, &amp;c. <hi>Our naturall fathers chaſtened us after their owne pleaſure; but God for our profit, that wee might be partakers of his holineſſe, &amp;c.</hi> Wherefore <hi>lift up the hands that hang downe, and the feeble knees, verſe</hi> 12. the Spirit convinceth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.28. <hi>that all things ſhall worke together for the beſt,</hi> that out of the eater ſhall come meat, and out of the ſtrong ſhall come ſweet, that God will ſmite this rock, <hi>viz.</hi> of hardſhip and trouble, and ſweet waters ſhall iſſue there from, and that he will make this wilderneſſe, <hi>viz.</hi> barren conditions in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of ontward comforts like the garden of <hi>Eden,</hi> in reſpect of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and ſpirituall Conſolations, <hi>that bleſſed is the man whom he cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteneth,</hi> Pſal. 94.12. that <hi>it is good for him that he is afflicted,</hi> and that God will make it a mercy unto him in the latter end, and that hee ſhall cordially and not complementally bleſſe the Lord for that ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering condition, and the ſweet experiments of his love therein, that bowels of love directs the rod, and infinite goodneſſe guides the hand.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Spirit of God perſwadeth <hi>that God as a father will but diſcipline him by afflictions, and thereby make him meet for his inheritance,</hi> an ingenuous beleever is not ſatisfied, that glory is purchaſed for him by the ſufferings of Chriſt; but is willing alſo to be made meet for that inheritance by his owne ſufferings; foraſmuch as it is the will of God that <hi>through many afflictions we muſt enter into the kingdome of heaven,</hi> the Lord Jeſus himſelfe ſanctifying that road by his own ſufferings, for this cauſe the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> with the reſt of the ſuffering Saints <hi>did not faint, becauſe though the outward man did periſh, yet the inner man is renued day by day:</hi> 2 Corinth. 4.16. What a beleever is in eſtate, he is in ſpirituals. And he reckons himſelf to riſe and fall as is the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition not of his outward but inner man: and herein is the differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between a formall and reall Chriſtian. Let the formaliſt abound in the outward man, he hath his will, but a beleever rejoyceth in his increaſe and thriving in the inner man, although it be gained
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:154500:8"/>by the periſhing of the outward man, and therefore they will <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce even in affliction, knowing that their affliction worketh patience, and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience experience, and experience hope, and hope maketh not aſhamed, becauſe the love of God is ſhed abroad in their hearts.</hi> This kindly working of their afflictions caufing them to thrive in the inner man, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by fitting them for glory, makes them ſweetly ſubmit to the will of God herein, it makes them ſay with ſweet ſubmiſſion of heart, <hi>Shall I not drinke of my Fathers cup?</hi> and ought I not <hi>firſt to ſuffer, and then to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into glory,</hi> as Chriſt did? the ſoul looks upon <hi>theſe outward afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are but for a ſeaſon, as working for them a farre more exceeding and eternall weight of glory,</hi> 2. Cor. 4.18. See here the diſproportion between one condition and the other, here is <hi>affliction,</hi> there is <hi>glory;</hi> here <hi>light affliction,</hi> there is <hi>weight of glory;</hi> here is <hi>momentany afflictions,</hi> there is <hi>eternity of glory.</hi> But that that is chiefly for our purpoſe in this text, is the influence that theſe afflictions have towards this glory in the word <hi>worketh,</hi> knowing that theſe afflictions, &amp;c. <hi>worketh for us a far more exceeding and eternall weight of glory:</hi> the ſuffering of Chriſt hath wrought it for us, but our own ſuffering worketh us for it, namely, by the ſweet growing of grace, and ſubduing of ſin, through theſe afflictions. And the Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>by afflictions</hi> (that is) through the kind working of afflictions, <hi>we are made partakers of his holineſſe.</hi> Hebr. 12.10. the Apoſtle vindicates a neceſſitie of afflictions to this purpoſe; <hi>Now for a ſeaſon (if need be) you are in afflictions through manifold temptations: if need be,</hi> that is, if the glorie of God, and your good doth require it. For ſo ſaith the context, <hi>that the triall of your faith being much more precious then gold that periſheth, though it be tried with fire, might be found unto praiſe, and honour, and glory of God at the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> 1 Pet. 1.7, 8. Let me appeal unto the experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Saints, whether they do not find and feel the quiet fruit of righteouſneſſe, the fruits of ſufferings; do not corruptions weaken? the ſweet influence of divine joy, dependance, patience, hope, meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, contentedneſſe, humilitie, and love to God increaſe more and more when they are under the croſſe? Thus the Spirit convinceth that God as a Father chaſtiſeth in meaſure, in love, and to fit them thereby for that glorie whereunto he hath appointed them. That is the ſecond particular, the Spirit convinceth, and comforteth by convincing, that God afflicteth as a Father, tender and loving in Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt comforteth Beleevers in evill
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154500:8"/>times, <hi>by opening, unfolding, and breaking up the exceeding rich and precious promiſes of the Goſpel, and applying the ſame unto the ſoule,</hi> the word of God is that <hi>River, the ſtreams whereof ſhall make glad the Citie of God:</hi> Pſal. 46.4. and theſe <hi>waters breakes out in the wilderneſſe, and theſe ſtreams in the deſart.</hi> Eſay 35.6. When poor <hi>Hagar</hi> was in the wilderneſſe with her child, and her accomodations gone, ſhe caſts her thirſtie infant under a ſhrub, and not able to heare the pittifull cryes of her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moaning babe, then doth the Angel of the Lord ſhew her a Well at hand, which was there before though not diſcerned, <hi>Gen.</hi> 21.16.19. juſt ſo when outward comforts are gone and ſpent, and the poore ſoule at a loſſe not knowing what to doe, but to lift up the eye to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God and weepe, why then doth the Lord by his Spirit ſhew them the ſweetneſſe and fulneſſe of ſuch and ſuch promiſes which before were not regarded. Tell me you plundered beleevers, that are driven (as <hi>Hagar</hi>) out of houſe and home, did you ever feel the ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the promiſes in that meaſure as you now feele them? have not theſe breaſts of Conſolation been ſweet and luſcious unto your taſts? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.50. ſaith <hi>David, This is my comfort in my affliction, thy word hath quickned me:</hi> and many ſuch paſſages as theſe, <hi>I had faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed had it not been for thy word. I rejoyce at thy word, as one that findeth great ſpoiles,</hi> 162. verſe. Hath not this been your caſe? have you not found thoſe treaſures in the promiſes (the ſpoiles of the victories of Jeſus Chriſt for you) which you never looked for? hath not the word of promiſe been more precious then gold, and ſweeter then the honey, yea, and the honey comb? have you ever ſeene your rich and glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous eſtate in Chriſt ſo cleare and evident as of late? hath not the Lord (fince he ſeparated you from your comforts, relations, eſtates, and employments, brought you as once he did <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>James,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> to the Mount, and transfigured himſelfe before you? ſhewed himſelfe in ſuch fulneſſe of glory and ſatisfaction, that you have ſaid, it is good for us to be here? hath not this time of trouble com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with the reſt of your former time of your lives been like <hi>Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> fleece, moſt ſweetly filled with the fatning dew of inward joy, and peace and comfort? did not many of the ſweet promiſes of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel before lye by you as uſeleſſe? did you ever know the meaning of them as of late? Experience is the beſt knowledge, and now have you not experience of the fulneſſe and truth of ſuch promiſes as theſe, <hi>In ill never leave thee nor forſake thee, I will be with thee, when th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u art in the fire, it ſhall not burn thee, and in the water, it ſhall not drown thee: I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154500:9"/>will be thy God all-ſufficient?</hi> Have you not ſeen the truth of this great promiſe, <hi>Truſt in the Lord, and do good, ſo ſhalt thou dwell in the land, and verily thou ſhalt be fed?</hi> Pſal. 37.3. Can you not read the truth of the promiſes in your experiences, as you did before the letter of them in your Bibles? Have you been a looſer by your ſufferings? Would you ſell (if it were poſſible) your experiences for your former injoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Can you not ſay with <hi>Solomon, Bleſſed be the Lord God of Iſrael, who hath with his hands fulfilled that which he ſpake with his mouth?</hi> 2 Chron. 6.4. That is the third way whereby the Spirit comforteth in evill times, by opening the treaſures of the promiſes, and by ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and chearing the heart with the comforts thereof.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the Spirit of Jeſus Chriſt comforteth beleevers in evill times, <hi>by tranſlating or carrying away the ſoul above out of the reach of all preſent troubles and ſorrows:</hi> ſo that as I may allude unto that of <hi>Philip</hi> in <hi>Act.</hi> 8.39. the Spirit of the Lord caught away <hi>Philip</hi> from the Eunuch, and he could ſee him no more; but he was found at Azotus: juſt ſo when troubles and ſorrows ariſe, the Spirit of the Lord catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away the heart and ſoul of beleevers, and theſe cannot find them. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.16. it is ſaid of a beleever, that <hi>he ſhall dwell on high, his place of defence ſhall be a munition of rocks.</hi> And in <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.14. the Church is ſaid to <hi>dwell in the clefts of the rocks:</hi> that is, in the wounds of Chriſt for ſecuritie from the guilt of ſin; in the attributes of God, for his ſecuritie in reſpect of the power and reach of ſin and ſorrow; having all the attributes of God as ſo many mightie Rocks for his ſafetie, and in or among the promiſes of the Coſpel for his inward chear and ſpirituall conſolation, and here ſhe <hi>dwels,</hi> it is the place of her habitation and conſtant abode, that no trouble or ſorrow can come at her, nor touch her at any time. <hi>Revel.</hi> 12.1. ſhe is ſaid to have <hi>the Moon under her feet.</hi> So that it is as eaſie for men, yea more caſie for men to hit the Moon, and pluck her out of the firmament, then it is to come at the Spouſe of Jeſus Chriſt. I have heard of ſome Indians that being ſcorched with the heat of the Sun, have thrown up their darts to hit it, which have returned upon themſelves; all their power and endeavours this way being tokens of their malice and madneſſe: And juſt ſo the holineſſe of the lives of the Saints dazling the eyes, and ſcorching the reputes of wicked men, moves them to caſt their darts of malice and perſecution againſt them to their own ruine; but they are as the Sun in the firmament which God himſelf hath eſtabliſhed, and all the world cannot remove it.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154500:9"/>
               <hi>Prov.</hi> 18.10. <hi>The Name of the Lord is a ſtrong tower, the righteous run into it, and are ſafe.</hi> The Spirit of God leadeth them into this tower, yea and quickly conveighs and carries them into this tower in time of trouble; ſo that they can enjoy themſelves in ſecuritie: God hath no more for his own ſecuritie but the Saints have the ſame. What hath God for his ſecuritie, peace and glorie, but his own bleſſed ſelf and infinite attributes, and that is the portion of beleevers. This made the Prophet <hi>David</hi> to ſay, <hi>God is our refuge, and ſtrength, a verie preſent help in troubles: therefore will not fear though the earth be removed, though the mountains be carried into the midſt of the Sea.</hi> Pſal. 46.1. what is the Reaſon, verſ. 7. <hi>The God of Jacob is our refuge:</hi> of <hi>Jacob,</hi> that is, of the Saints in their loweſt eſtate and condition. For ſo often in Scripture when the Saints are ſet forth in their weakneſſe, it is by the name of <hi>Jacob,</hi> as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 41.14. <hi>Fear not thou worm</hi> Jacob; now <hi>the God of Jacob is our refuge:</hi> and ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.2. <hi>The Lord is my rock, and my fortreſſe, and my high tower.</hi> Why now carnall men and meer formaliſts obſerves the letter of theſe things, but know not the meaning of it; It is common and ordinarie to ſay, the Lord is our help and our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, our ſhield, our tower, &amp;c. but it is rare to find a man able to ſhew from his own inward and perſonall experience, how the Spirit of God conveighs him in the time of troubles thus unto God as unto a tower, which is, I conceive, after this method. Firſt, when trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles do ariſe, the Spirit of God preſently minds the ſoul where is his ſecuritie, where he muſt be ſafe, as the poore Conies which makes their houſes in the Rocks: <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.26. when ſhe is in danger ſhe preſently minds her hole; ſo doth Beleevers at the firſt approach of trouble: for this indeed is naturall in time of ſudden ſurpriſe to think upon that which we make our ſtay and our hope. Carnall men minds many things when they are ſurpriſed, and God in the laſt place, and after the meaneſt and loweſt thoughts and hopes, with ſuch thoughts that yeelds poore relief: But the Spirit of God minds the Saints of God in the firſt place, and this preſently yeelds peace and quietneſſe, and other means of comfort are minded in ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation unto him. When ſad and miſerable times were revealed unto <hi>Habbakkuk,</hi> the hearing whereof made his belly to tremble, and rottenneſſe to enter into his bones, to conſider, that the fig-tree ſhould not bloſſom, nor fruit in the vine, the labour of the olive ſhould fail, no meat in the fields, no flocks in the fold, nor heards in the ſtall, his heart preſently thought upon the Lord, in whom he
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:154500:10"/>would <hi>rejoyce, and joy in the God of his ſalvation.</hi> Habak. 3.16, 17, 18. And many the like inſtances from Scripture may be given, to prove that the Spirit of God ſo ſoon as troubles do begin, lifts up the thoughts, and minds of beleevers to conſider where muſt be their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie; they hear the Spirit of God ſay unto them, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 26.20. <hi>Come my people, enter thou in thy chambers, ſhut the doores upon thee, hide thy ſelf as it were for a little moment, untill the indignation he over-paſt. My people,</hi> the ſpirit ſpeaks moſt comfortably, and in moſt aſſured lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, in troubleſome time, <hi>enter into thy chambers, chambers</hi> are places of reſt and quietneſſe; <hi>chambers</hi> in the plurall number, that is, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the ſeverall grounds of your peace, the attributes of God, the blood of Chriſt, the promiſes of the Goſpel. <hi>Shut the doores,</hi> that is, lock thy ſelf up in God by faith, keep out unbelief. <hi>Hide thy ſelf, viz.</hi> in God, <hi>untill the indignation, viz.</hi> theſe troubles and ſorrows be gone. That is the firſt thing.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as the Spirit of God minds the ſoul where his ſecuritie is, ſo <hi>it minds him of the way, whereby he may come at it, and that is Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It were to little purpoſe to be nigh a Rock, and cannot find the hole to run in unto it; to be neer a Caſtle when we are purſued, and cannot find the doore that leadeth into it. God he is a Rock, and Jeſus Chriſt is the hole of the Rock: God is a tower, and Jeſus Chriſt he is the doore in unto him. <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.9. <hi>I am the doore,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> unto the Father: <hi>By me if any man enter he ſhall be ſaved; viz.</hi> from ſin and ſorrow here and hereafter, and <hi>he ſhall go in and out and find paſture.</hi> Poore carnall men are like the blinded Sodomites about <hi>Lots</hi> houſe, they grope and buz up and down, but cannot find the way in. They are neer unto God, and God is neer unto them, and they run about thinking to come in at God, by their prayers, and their good meaning, and their duties, and qualifications: But alas! they cannot find the doore. <hi>No man cometh unto the Father but by me,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.6. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto the Father,</hi> that is, God in his rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of love and mercie; for other wayes every man good and bad ſhal come before God at the laſt day: So that the Spirit of God when troubles do ariſe, minds the ſoul of God wherein is his ſecuritie, and of Jeſus Chriſt as an open doore into his God. Tell me you that have experience of the ſecrets of God, did you ever find more ſweet and precious thoughts of Jeſus Chriſt, then when troubles have aroſe? Did not the Spirit of God as it were drive &amp; force you againſt your ſecret unbelief, and backwardneſſe in through Jeſus Chriſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Father?</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:154500:10"/>
            <p>Thirdly, as the Spirit of God mindes the ſoule where is his ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and the way to come at it, ſo in the third place <hi>it gives inward ſecret life and ſtrength, and ſpirituall abillities to flie unto God, in and through Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It is in vaine for a man to ſee a tower when the enemy is purſuing, and to ſee the doore open, if he hath no legs nor ſtrength to runne in unto it: but the Spirit of God gives ſpirit, and life, and ſtrength to make uſe of God through Jeſus Chriſt for his ſupport and comfort. That fore named place of <hi>Habakuk</hi> 3.19. when he looked upon God as his ſalvation, he addeth, <hi>hee ſhall make my feet as Hindes feet: viz.</hi> ſwift and ſpeedie, to carry mee to my <hi>high places, viz.</hi> unto God my high tower, God gives unto the ſoule the <hi>wings of a Dove,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> hath it, <hi>Pſalme</hi> 55.6. <hi>viz.</hi> of his Spirit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>he flies away and is at reſt.</hi> Tell me you experienced holy ones, did you ever feele the ſtrength of faith more glorious in you, then ſince theſe troubles came upon you? have you not found your faith a great deale weaker under leſſer troubles then now, when happily you are plundered of all you have?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, as the Spirit of God ſhewes the ſoule where his ſccuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is, and the doore hereunto, and gives legs and ſpirit to run unto it, it ſhewes God and Jeſus Chriſt, and brings the ſoule unto God through Chriſt: So in the fourth place, <hi>it enables the ſouleta treat with God in prayer, and to prevaile with him to be his ſecuritie, his rocke, his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, &amp;c.</hi> The Spirit of Chriſt moves the ſoule towards God through Chriſt, and then ſuggeſts and dictates its requeſt unto him, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Becauſe you are ſonnes, God hath ſent forth the Spirit of his Sonne into your hearts, whereby you cry, Abba, Father:</hi> the Saints of God, <hi>are ſons of God. Ye are ſons,</hi> ſaith the Text, the free grace of God maketh them ſo by adoption, the Spirit of God makes them ſo by the infuſion of the Divine Nature, <hi>viz.</hi> ſo farr as communicable; the ſons of God have the Spirit of Chriſt, <hi>becauſe you are ſonnes, God hath ſent forth the Spirit of his Son into your hearts,</hi> where hee gives the priviledges of his Sonne, he gives the Spirit of his Sonne; <hi>into their hearts,</hi> not onely the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of his Sonne into their heads, and the confeſſion of his Sonne into their tongues; but the Spirit of his Sonne <hi>into their hearts, whereby ye cry,</hi> the Spirit of Chriſt is a ſpirit of prayer, and of fervency in prayer, <hi>ye cry; Abba, Father,</hi> the Spirit of Chriſt is the Spirit of adopti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and that to the Greeks as well as to the Jewes, and the Spirit per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades that now the ſonnes of God are not onely of the Jewes, but the Gentiles, and that hee is a Father to all that call upon him in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154500:11"/>Truth, whether Jewes or Greekes, and therefore the Apoſtle here ſpeaketh in the language both of the Jewes and Greekes, <hi>viz.</hi> the whole world, <hi>Abba Father,</hi> the maine that we note here to our pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe is, that the Spirit of Chriſt is a Spirit of prayer, and it cheares the ſoule in time of trouble by enabling it to powre out it ſelfe unto the Lord in prayer, which is a ſweet ſupporting exerciſe, God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands <hi>in nothing to be carefull; but in every thing to let our requeſts be made knowne unto him in giving of thankes,</hi> Philip. 4.6. God would have his people live in quietneſſe, not in anxious troubles, and ſolicitous cares of the minde, <hi>be ſo carefull for nothing,</hi> turne not your troubles into cares; but into prayers, <hi>in every thing by prayer and ſupplication,</hi> let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing occaſion prayer and ſupplication, and let your prayers be alwayes daſht with <hi>thanks-giving,</hi> your preſent wants may move your prayers and earneſt requeſts, <hi>your ſupplications,</hi> and your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent enjoyments calls for your <hi>thanks-giving:</hi> This God commands in many places in the holy Scriptures, <hi>Open thy mouth wide, I will fill it,</hi> Pſal. 81.10. we cannot out pray Gods power and goodneſſe; No, <hi>he is able</hi> and therefore willing <hi>to doe abundantly above all that we are able to aske or thinke,</hi> Epheſ. 3.20. I might bring in many more places, as that in the <hi>Canticles</hi> 2.14. <hi>Let me ſee thy face, let me heare thy voice,</hi> and againe, <hi>Call upon me in the day of trouble I will heare thee,</hi> and turne thy prayer into prayſes, <hi>thou ſhalt praiſe me,</hi> Pſal. 50.15. The Spirit puts the ſoule into an improvement of theſe incouragements in this duty. And here againe, let me appeale unto you, Oh ye afflicted and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted Saints, did you ever feele the Spirit of prayer ſo ſwectly breathing in your ſouls, as ſince your troubles? Have you not found that freeneſſe and inlargedneſſe of ſpirit, which you neuer found in all the dayes of your pilgrimage? cannot many a ſecret corner witneſſe ſuch pantings, ſuch movings, ſuch powring forth of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and teares, and holy and heavenly affections as you never knew before? and hath not this been a moſt ſweet ſtrengthning ordinance unto you, though God hath touched you as it were in the hollow of your thigh, I mean your eſtate, your friends, and outward com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, that perhaps you may halt all the dayes of your life in reſpect thereof, yet have you not had ſuch a bleſſing through your wraſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with God, as that you would not want it for all your former wonted comforts? That is the fourth particuler.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, as the Spirit of God doth minde the ſoule of God, his tower of Jeſus Chriſt the doore into it, gives ſtrength to come unto
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154500:11"/>it, enables to pray and prevaile with God for protection, and ſupplies: ſo in the laſt place, <hi>the ſpirit proves in the ſoule grace ſufficient to ſupport, to uphold during the trouble it lies under,</hi> 2. Cor. 12.9. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> lying under ſome great preſſure of ſpirit, what it was is the different judgement of many godly learned, yet it drove him unto God in Chriſt, and his anſwere was, <hi>that the grace of God was ſufficient for him: the grace of God,</hi> that is, the favour of God is ſufficient to appeaſe and ſatisfie his conſcience from guilt; and <hi>the grace of God,</hi> that is, the Spirit of grace is ſufficient to ſupport, and keepe up the heart, notwithſtanding the power of the affliction. This Spirit of Chriſt convaies as it were the influence of Gods attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes, his power, goodneſſe, and mercy, and the influence of Chriſts Offices and Merits, and applyes, and brings home the ſweet and luſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious promiſes, and the ſtrength of ſupporting ordinances in that experimentall and ſutable manner unto the condition of the ſoule, that no man knowes the meaning hereof but ſpirituall Chriſtians indeed. And tell me againe, O ye afflicted of the Lord, have you not felt the ſecret workings of the attributes of God, Offices, Blood, and Merits of Chriſt, the Promiſes of the Goſpel, and Ordinances of Gods Worſhip, like the ſtill dew of heaven dropping upon your ſoules, and making you fruitfull in <hi>all peace and joy in beleeving,</hi> filling you with patience, meekeneſſe, and all other graces of the Spirit <hi>to the praiſe of his grace?</hi> And have not you beene in reſpect of your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and ſpirituall ſecurity like God himſelfe, a bove all ſtorms, and troubles belowe, able to laugh them to ſcorne? have you not felt ſuch <hi>refreſhings to come from the preſence of the Lord,</hi> which have been as <hi>waters out of a rock in a thirſty land?</hi> Have you not been hereby able to ſee all things beneath you? and your ſelves like God in ſecuritie, when clouds and darkneſſe have beene round about you, ſolacing your ſelves in your God, pertaking of that fulneſſe of joy, and drinking from thoſe rivers of pleaſure which are in his preſence for evermore? And that is the fourth generall anſwer to the ſecond generall queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, namely, how the Spirit comforteth beleevers in evill times, <hi>viz. by t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anſlating and carrying them above the reach of all trouble and ſorrows here belowe, and ſetting them in God as in a ſure rock and defence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, the Spirit comforteth Beleevers in evill times <hi>by ſetting be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, and clearing up unto them the glory of, and their intereſt in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie of the other world;</hi> the inheritance incorruptible, undefiled, that fadeth not away, reſerved for them in the heavens, revealed
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154500:12"/>unto them by the Spirit of Chriſt, is that <hi>wherein they greatly rejoyce, though now for a ſeaſon if need be, they are in heavineſſe through manifold temptations:</hi> 1 Pet. 1.4.6. verſes, thoſe glorious things <hi>which eye hath not ſeen, nor eare heard, nor mans beart conceive, prepared by God for them that love him, and revealed by the Spirit:</hi> 1 Cor. 2.10. God having given them the Spirit that <hi>they may know the things that are given to them of God:</hi> verſe 12. Theſe things, I ſay, bear up the heart in evill times; this made <hi>Steven</hi> ſeeing the glory of God, and Jeſus Chriſt ſtanding at the right hand of God, and all the glorious viſion of heaven open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him, inſenſible of that ſtonie ſtrome by which he was tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated unto that glory: quietly refigning his ſoul unto God, and beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging mercie for thoſe that killed him. <hi>Act.</hi> 7.60. This was that that made thoſe holy Martyrs in the old time (an extract of the ſtorie whereof we have in the 11. to the <hi>Hebr.</hi>) to indure <hi>cruell mockings, and ſcourgings, bonds and impriſonments, tortures and ſtonings, ſawing in ſunder, and to be killed with ſwords, wandring up and down in ſheep skins, and goats skins, being deſtitute, afflicted, tormented.</hi> Hebr. 11.35, 36, 37. viz. <hi>They looked after a Countrey</hi> better then this world, even heavenly, and a <hi>City prepared for them by God,</hi> verſe 16. Their eyes being fixed and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by the Spirit, <hi>upon the recompence of the reward,</hi> verſe 26. This made both them, and the Lord Jeſus himſelf, <hi>with patience to run the race that was ſet before them, to indure the croſſe, and to deſpiſe the ſhame:</hi> viz. the <hi>joy that was ſet before them,</hi> Hebr. 12.12. And this was that, that made the Apoſtles in after times, not to faint in the ſad, various, and manifold periſhings of their outward man, namely, their <hi>looking not at the things that are ſeen, but at the things that are not ſeen.</hi> 2 Cor. 4.16, 17, 18. And their certain knowledge that <hi>when their earthly tabernacles were diſſolved, they had a building of God, an houſe not made with hands, but eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall in the heavens.</hi> 2 Cor. 5.1. This made them rejoyce in partaking with the ſufferings of Chriſt, becauſe they knew that <hi>when his glory ſhould appear, they ſhould be glad alſo with exceeding joy.</hi> 1 Pet. 4.13. and that <hi>if they ſuffered with Chriſt, they ſhould alſo reigne with him:</hi> 2 Tim. 2.12. And this alſo made the Saints of God after the Apoſtles times, in the time of the ten Perſecutions, to indure burning, ſtoning, fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, roaſting, ſcalding, cutting, whipping with hot wiers, tearing in peeces with wild beaſts, boring out of eyes, tearing of the fleſh from the bones with hot pincers, and iron inſtruments, plucking out of their bowels, and all other exquiſite tortures as divelliſh cruell heart of men, taught by the Devill, himſelf, could invent; the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154500:12"/>ſtories whereof are extant, which would make our very hearts to ake and bleed, yea enough to overcome our very thoughts even unto ſwounding, to read and beleeve the ſame; yet the Spirit of God made them able, by ſhewing them the glory of <hi>a better reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> as the Apoſtle hath it: <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.35. And this was that, that made likewiſe the people of God under Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes of later times, to indure ſuch cruell burnings, &amp;c. even the glory of another life; this made a burning flame a bed of roſes, and this was light in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and life in death unto them. And again, I appeal unto you, O ye that now fill up the reſt of the ſufferings of Chriſt; do ye not feel the viſion of glory chearing up your hearts, and ſilling you with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward glory and joy? Did you ever ſee the heavens ſo clear over your heads as now? Doth not your waiting for the hope of the glorie of God, raiſe up your hearts? Doth not this make you look upon your preſent troubles, and loſſes of your eſtates and comforts with more inward joy, and peace, and quietneſſe of ſpirit, then ever you could look upon them when you had them? Hath not God by quitting you of your eſtates and large enjoyments here belowe, quitted you likewiſe of a great deal of trouble and perplexitie, and made you exult in the enjoyment of himſelf in his Son, by his Spirit, and of al choſe giorious things wherunto he hath reſerved you? wel: that is the 5. Anſwer to the Queſtion, the Spirit comforteth Beleevers in evill times, by ſetting before them the glory of another world.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the Spirit of Chriſt comforteth Beleevers in evill times, by furniſhing them with, and enabling them to the exerciſe of thoſe ſuffering gifts and graces, that are ſuitable unto ſuch a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. Afflicted Saints are <hi>ſtrengthened with all might according to the glorious power of God, unto all patience, and long-ſuffering with joyfulneſſe.</hi> Coloſ. 1.11. They are in themſelves weak, but of weak God makes them ſtrong; and therefore they <hi>are ſtrengthened with all might:</hi> God hath no ſtrength beyond <hi>all might,</hi> and beleevers in God <hi>are ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ened with all might,</hi> unto <hi>patience,</hi> the Saints <hi>have need of patience;</hi> unto <hi>all patievce,</hi> they are obnoxious unto all troubles, and therefore need <hi>all patience and long-ſuffering:</hi> not patience for a time, but with perſeverance, even <hi>long-ſuffering,</hi> and that not with grief and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, but <hi>with joyfulneſſe.</hi> Patience imply ſorrows, and comforts imply ſufferings, and yet <hi>with joyfulneſſe:</hi> for the truth is, the verie grace of patience is more precious then deliverance, and freedome from the trouble, which is the cauſe thereof. The Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Rom.</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:154500:13"/>5.3. <hi>We glory in tribulation:</hi> why ſo? <hi>becauſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>tribulation work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth patience, and patience experience, and experience hope.</hi> It is a beleevers joy, and crown of rejoycing, to ſee the thriving of the inner man; and that his heart, and every part there, may be as a fruitfull gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, ſweetly flouriſhing with the beds of ſpices; he will pray and deſire, that <hi>North wind, viz.</hi> cold winter afflictions, or <hi>South wind, viz.</hi> the warme comforts of the inner or outward man, may <hi>blowe</hi> upon it. <hi>Song</hi> 4.16. And it will <hi>glory</hi> even <hi>in afflictions,</hi> when the fruit thereof ſhall be ſuch proſperity in the inner man. If ſo be that the bleſſed proſperitie of afflictions ſhall be ſuch a ſweet of-ſpring, as that as <hi>Abraham</hi> begat <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac</hi> begat <hi>Jacob.</hi> &amp;c. So afflictions ſhall beget patience, and patience experience, and experience hope, &amp;c. Surely a beleever cannot chuſe but rejoyce, yea glory in afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as much as ever <hi>Sarah</hi> did rejoyce and glory in her great belly: this was that <hi>renuing in the inner man day by day,</hi> which made <hi>Paul,</hi> and the reſt of the ſuffering Saints to rejoyce, <hi>though their outward man did periſh.</hi> 2 Cor. 4.16. And hence it is that they <hi>count it all joy when that they fall into divers temptations, knowing that the triall of their faith work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth patience,</hi> and <hi>patience having its perfect work, maketh them perfect, and intire wanting nothing.</hi> Jam. 1.2.3. A ſpirituall growth in the inner man, is ſo much the more acceptable unto a beleever above all out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward injoyments, by how much the more it is more precious in it ſelf then they: Outward bleſſings are <hi>Eſau</hi> his portion; but God is the portion of his Saints, and the more of God they have, <hi>viz.</hi> of his divine communicable nature, the richer they are; if they can ſee the light of Gods countenance ſhining upon them, and the work of his Spirit thriving in them; they have enough, and will rejoyce in that condition wherein theſe proſper, though it be moſt irkſome to their frail fleſh: and here again I call for your experiences, you refined Saints, by the fiery triall, did you ever feel God ſo powerfull in you, the work of his Spirit ſo ſtrong in you, in patience, meekneſſe, hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie, gentleneſſe, dependance upon God, &amp;c. as you have done ſince you have been ſtript of your late comforts? Did you not know the time, that the ſmalleſt croſſe, and trouble in your eſtates made you peeviſh, paſſionate, and froward? and now you can look upon the ſpoiling of your whole eſtate with joy? Did you not know the time, when the beſt food, eaſieſt lodging, coſtly garments, and many friends, with many other accommodations could not ſatisfie and content you? and you are now ſatisfied, and can bleſſe God, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154500:13"/>thank your friends, for a meals meat, a ſuit of clothes, a little mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, a nights lodging, a mean houſe to hide your heads in, and now brown bread and the Goſpel is good fare with you. The time was when you thought your ſelves high and great men; and that every man wrong'd you if he came not to you with cap, and knee, at eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie word looking haply, upon your inferiours in eſtate, though ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours in grace, with mean thoughts and diſreſpect, but now you hugge them in your boſoms, and bleſſe God for their ſocietie, and Chriſtian company; and is not this a ſweet chearing? Would you want this precious ſpirituall work upon your hearts, for all your glorie? Well, this is the laſt way that I ſhall note, whereby the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit comforteth Beleevers in evil times: <hi>viz.</hi> by furniſhing them with, and enabling them unto the exerciſe of thoſe ſuitable gifts, and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces fit for a ſuffering condition. And ſo much for the ſecond generall Queſtion, how the Spirit comforteth Beleevers in evill times.</p>
            <p>The third generall Queſtion is, <hi>How the Spirit of Chriſt may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned from the ſpirit of deluſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This indeed is one of the moſt concerning Queries in all the world, as will appear, if you note theſe brief conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>If any man hath not the Spirit of Chriſt, he is none of his:</hi> Rom. 8.9. <hi>viz.</hi> for the preſent in his own knowledge, and to his own ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
            <p>Secondly, if any man hath not the Spirit of Chriſt, he cannot worſhip him in ſpirit, and in truth; ſo that <hi>to kill an ox</hi> in ſacrifice is no more acceptable unto God, <hi>then killing a man. His ſacrificing a lamb is as if he cut off a dogs neck, his oblation is as ſwines blood, his incenſe is as bleſſing an Idol:</hi> Iſa. 66.3. that is, not onely not acceptable unto God, but every way as abominable as theſe provocations.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if a man hath not the Spirit, <hi>he is left alone in all his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and perplexities:</hi> for there is no meet help, and comfort for a man, but the Spirit. When God made man at firſt, having made the world, behold all was good ſave one; and that was for man to be alone: <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 2.18. <hi>But now among all the creatures was not found an help meet for him:</hi> verſe 20. Even ſo it is not good to be alone, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 1.10. that is, alone, to bear all his croſſes and troubles. Now among all other comforters is not found an help, and comforter meet for man, and therefore God gives his people the Spirit. <hi>Adam</hi> was above the capac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ie of all other creatures here belowe, and therefore he muſt have an help of his own qualitie, and conſideration: juſt ſo the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154500:14"/>whole world is beneath the ſoul of man; and therefore it muſt be ſomething like it ſelf that muſt be a ſuitable good, and that is the Spirit of Chriſt, which indeed differeth from <hi>Adams</hi> help in this chiefly:
<note place="margin">☞</note>
               <hi>viz.</hi> that when God made man at firſt, his help was the weaker veſſel, by occaſion whereof, he fell; but now in reſtoring man, God intending to make his recoverie more glorious then at firſt, his help is the ſtronger: <hi>viz.</hi> the ſtrong God himſelf by his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit within.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, confider, if a man hath not the Spirit of Chriſt, <hi>the day of his death will be a bitter day unto him:</hi> even the houre, and power of darkneſſe, when the whole world ſhall vaniſh in his own viſion, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſenſible of nothing but fear, and dread, and a guilty Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and of Satan readie to prey upon his trembling ſoul, readie to expire.</p>
            <p>Digeſt theſe conſidtrations, with ſuch like, ſeriouſly in your thoughts; and let them have their own proper working upon your ſpirit: Conſider, are you able to bear it, that Chriſt and you ſhould have no intereſt each in other? that all your prayers, and tears, and duties of all kinds, ſhall riſe up againſt you one day; have you not ſin enough to damne you, but your duties muſt do it? are you able to be alone in your miſeries? are not the Heavens black over your heads, and the Earth bloodie under your feet? do you not ſee the hils to quake, and the mountains hurl'd into the midſt of the Seas? is there not ſuch a Concuſſion of Kingdoms, Cities, Countreys, which threatens a confuſion of all? Do you not ſee God coming like an armed man againſt you, attended with a black guard of bloodie warre, famine, plagues, peſtilences, and the bitter conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of theſe? Do you not expect death every day, when God is coming with his judgements as with a fieth to mowe down the kingdom before him? and can you bear the thoughts of death without the Spirit to chear you, and ſupport you? How might all this put us all upon inquiſition, whether we have the Spirit of Chriſt? Before we come to the ſolution of this grand Queſtion. Ssme things are to be premiſed by way of caution.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that there are many in the world that think they have the Spirit of Chriſt, and it is nothing ſo.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that ſome there are that have the Spirit of Chriſt, and know it not.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, that it is very poſſible to know that a man hath the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Chriſt.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:154500:14"/>
            <p>Fourthly, that it is a very hard and difficult thing to find it out.</p>
            <p>All and every one of theſe premiſes, and cautions, may be clearly argued out both from manifeſt Scriptures, and Reaſons, and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations; which will (if proſecuted accordingly) be a too great digreſſion from the thing intended, and beſides much conviction in them all, is extant in the Labours of many godly and holy mens writings.</p>
            <p>There is a great deale of difference in the judgements of ſome godly men, whether a mans Juſtification may bee knowne by his Sanctification, and by the markes and fignes of Sanctification. It were to bee wiſht that both the one partie and the other, yea the whole generation of holy ones, the Sonnes of unitie, would ſtudie unitie among themſelves, and make conſcience of that Apoſtolicall Injunction, ſo far as in them lieth, 1. Theſſ. 4.11. <hi>Studie to be quiet,</hi> and 1. Pet. 3.8. <hi>Be ye all of one minde, having compaſſion one of another, love as brethren.</hi> Surely if we had <hi>compaſſion one of another,</hi> eſpecially in theſe times, when our diviſions are both the ſtudie, and advantages of our bloody enemies, we would <hi>be all of one minde,</hi> at leaſt ſo far as we reveale our ſelves to the world, it is very ſad to ſee men, even holy doubtleſſe, and godly, to be ſo farre from ſtudying to be quiet, that they ſtudy to oppoſe and to differ, and it is a very acceptable thing unto them to differ from their brethren, and to blaze the ſame. (I would not be miſtaken) a tender conſcience an inquiring and ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit after the things of Jeſus Chriſt is very commendable; but yet with ſpeciall reſpects to the Community of Chriſt and all his Churches, and the truth is, we ſuffer much diſadvantage by our neglect this way. But to returne to the buſineſſe in hand, this I think will be granted, that for a man to know his intereſt in God, and the truth of the Spirit in his heart, is a part of Sanctification; whether it be by the teſtimony of the Spirit, or any other way, and therefore at leaſt in ſome ſence it is to be granted, that the knowledge of our Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification is by the knowledge of our Sanctification.</p>
            <p>Againe, this I thinke will be likewiſe granted, that no man can be aſſured of his Juſtification, and not be ſanctified, that hee cannot know his Juſtification without Sanctification, it is very true, that it is a very hard and difficult thing to finde out the truth of holines, and ſupernaturall worke of Gods Spirit in the ſoule, the heart of man be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo deceitfull above all things, and there being ſo many counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feit quallifications, and common gifts, and it is to be granted alſo,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154500:15"/>that many deluded hypocrites think great matters of their conceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed holineſſe, from ſuch and ſuch qualliſications wrought within them, and ſuch and ſuch things done by them; and many alſo whoſe hearts are moſt upright with their God, yet through ignorance of Jeſus Chriſt, and conſciouſneſſe of their owne guilt, misjudge of their owne happie eſtate, and ſo erre on the other hand; yet this I thinke, is not to be denyed, <hi>viz.</hi> that the meaneſt Saints have peculiar and fingular workes of the Spirit in their very worſt condition of ſoule, which the moſt glorious hypocrites in the world, never had in their beſt condition, and greateſt inlargements in their hearts. Theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations being premiſed, the reſult herein will be this; that as in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward quallifications are to be heeded, I meane in uſing them as ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfactory markes of an undoubted condition,
<note place="margin">☞</note> ſound and good in Jeſus Chriſt; ſo on the other hand, they are not altogether to be neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected as uſeleſſe for ſuch a purpoſe: for doubtleſſe if men will take that paines with their ſpirits as they may doe, they may in a very probable, if not certaine way, have much ſatisfaction in reſpect of the ſtate of their ſoules: otherwiſe I know not how to uſe and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove that place of the Apoſtle, John 13.20.21. <hi>If our hearts condemne us, God is greater then our hearts; if our hearts condemne us not, then have wee confidence before God.</hi> So in <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. and many ſuch like places, and therefore I take leave to give my anſwer to the queſtion in hand, with a very ſpeciall reſpect to what the Spirit of God wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the ſoul. To the queſtion therefore, how a man may know the truth of the Spirit in his heart. I anſwer.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>The Spirit of Chriſt in the heart, is Chriſt ſpiritually in the heart,</hi> that is, Conſider Chriſt in every reſpect, and there is an anſwerable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe thereof in the heart of the beleever. Chriſt is conſiderable in his Natures, Conception, Birth, Life, Death, Buriall, Reſurrection, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cention, and Interceſſion at the right hand of God the Father, and in his Offices, and there is a certaine conſimilitude of every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler in the heart of a ſpirituall man.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the Natures of Chriſt, he was God and Man, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.47. <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.10. So beleevers as they are true men, ſo likewiſe are they <hi>partakers of the divine Nature,</hi> ſo farre as Communicable; God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe dwelling in them, <hi>viz.</hi> by his Spirit, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4. <hi>John</hi> 14.17.</p>
            <p>Secondly, For the Conception of Chriſt; hee was Conceived by the holy Ghoſt, not by any meanes of the Virgin, yet not againſt, or without her, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.35. Even ſo Chriſt in a beleever is Conceived,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:154500:15"/>
               <hi>Not of blood, nor of the will of the fleſh, nor of the will of man, but of God.</hi> John 1.13.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Conſider Chriſt in his Birth, elected before the world, by the Father, but borne in fulneſſe of time, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.4. even ſo belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers <hi>according to the good pleaſure of God which he purpoſed in himſelfe, in fulnes of time are gathered together,</hi> as the Apoſtle hath it, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.9, 10.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Looke upon the Life of Chriſt, from firſt to laſt, hee did and ſuffered all things, and that with all delight and complacency, with reference to his Fathers will, <hi>John</hi> 4.33. <hi>John</hi> 5.30. <hi>Luke</hi> 22.42. Even ſo the Spirit of Chriſt frameth the whole of man ſo farre as he is ſpirituall to do and ſuffer all, and that with delight in reference unto the will of God. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Galat.</hi> 4.12. &amp;c. And as the Law of God was written in the heart of Chriſt, which made him naturally content, and willing to do the will of God: <hi>Hebr.</hi> 10.7. Even ſo the Law of God is written in the heart of beleevers, which makes them willing, and chearfull in doing the will of God. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8.10, 11.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Look upon the ſufferings of Chriſt, that hath a manifold influence and operation in the ſoul; as firſt, <hi>to pacifie and quiet the heart:</hi> Chriſt by his eternall Spirit tendreth his blood to pacifie God ſitting in the throne of Juſtice, in the ſeat of glory. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9.14. And the Spirit of Chriſt tendreth as it were the ſame blood unto the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience (Gods vice-gerent) to the ſatisfaction and pacification ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: All the oblations in the world, though they had been ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand rivers of oyl, could not have ſatisfied Divine Juſtice, nothing but the blood of Chriſt; nor that too, had it not been offered up by the eternall Spirit, which was as it were the Altar ſanctifying the gift and offering; So no means in the world, qualifications, duties, promiſes, ordinances, can ſatisfie a ſin-ſeeing conſcience, but the blood of Chriſt; and that alſo muſt be tendred unto it by the Spirit of Chriſt: The truth is, nothing can ſatisfie an enlightned conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence but that that did ſatisfie God himſelf, which is Chriſt diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered in the excellencie of his merits; and this is by the tendring the ſame through the Spirit, by which Chriſt is thus diſcovered. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the death of Chriſt hath another influence and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude in the ſoul, and <hi>that is the crucifying of the body of ſin;</hi> and that, firſt by way of a holy revenge for the ſhedding of Chriſts blood. Sin perſued Chriſt even unto the Croſſe; the Spirit perſues ſin even to the Croſſe alſo. <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.24. <hi>They that are Chriſts, have crucified the fleſh
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154500:16"/>with the affections and luſts thereof.</hi> And again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13. <hi>If ye through the Spirit mortifie the deeds of the fleſh, ye ſhall live.</hi> Secondly, there is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veighed a certain ſecret ennergettical power, and derived in a ſweet ſpirituall manner from the death of Chriſt, (<hi>viz.</hi> by ſerious contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation and belief thereof) to kill, and mortifie ſin. <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.6. <hi>Our old man was crucified with him, that the body of ſin might be deſtroyed.</hi> And <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Galat.</hi> 2.20. <hi>I am crucified with Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the blood of Chriſt is as it were a ſecret, and yet ſenſible bath wherein the ſoul is healed, and cured, and cleanſed, ſteeped and rinſed from the filth and guilt of ſin. This blood is that <hi>fountain opened for ſin, and for uncleanneſſe, to waſh in, Zach.</hi> 13.1. wherein the Saints <hi>are waſhed.</hi> 1 Cor. 6.11. and this <hi>purgeth their conſciences from dead works to ſerve the living God.</hi> Hebr. 9.14.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the blood of Chriſt is the life of the ſoul, that is, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for the life of the ſoul; <hi>His fleſh is meat indeed, and his blood is drink indeed.</hi> Joh. 6.55. <hi>indeed,</hi> that is in reſpect of everlaſting nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment that flows from it; for, ſaith he, <hi>he that eateth me, ſhall live by me:</hi> verſ. 57. <hi>He that drinketh my blood ſhall never thirſt.</hi> Joh. 4.14. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Chriſt died, we live: <hi>viz.</hi> in reſpect of Juſtification; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he liveth, we ſhall live, in reſpect of ſanctification. <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.19. Thus in many particulars, the death of Chriſt hath a bleſſed influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in the hearts of the Saints, which is the fifth Conſideration concerning Chriſt in the ſoul, in reſpect of his ſufferings.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, conſider Chriſt in reſpect, as of death, ſo of his buriall; the very grave of Chriſt hath an operation in the heart: <hi>We are buri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with him,</hi> Gal. 6.4. Coloſ. 2.12. The old man doth by little and little moulder away as it were in the grave of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Seventhly, the reſurrection of Chriſt hath likewiſe an influence in the ſoul, <hi>viz.</hi> to raiſe it up to a new, ſpirituall, and holy life. We are ſaid to <hi>be raiſed up together with Chriſt:</hi> Epheſ. 2.6. <hi>He that raiſed up Chriſt from the dead, ſhall quicken your mortall bodies by his Spirit that dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth in you.</hi> Rom. 8.11. The truth is, there are moſt glorious and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious operations, and influences of the reſurrection of Chriſt in the heart, which would be too large now to inſiſt upon.</p>
            <p>Eightly, the aſcention of Chriſt is ſeen alſo in its operation in the ſoul, <hi>viz.</hi> to draw up our hearts, and deſires, and expectations hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven-wards. <hi>Col.</hi> 1.2. this is by the Spirit.</p>
            <p>Ninthly and laſtly, the very ſeſſion of Chriſt at the right hand of God, and his interceding there for us, is felt in the ſoul (the Spirit
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154500:16"/>of God leading it into the preſence of God, and ſetting it as it were at the <hi>right hand</hi> of the Father among the ſheep, not among goats: <hi>Matth.</hi> 25. giving it all boldneſſe, even as a right hand favourite; and there <hi>making interceſſion with ſighs and groans that cannot be expreſſed.</hi> Rom. 8.16. Thus you ſee the firſt generall Anſwer to this third ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Queſtion: <hi>viz.</hi> how might we know the Spirit of Chriſt in the ſoul, from the ſpirit of deluſion. Anſwer. <hi>The Spirit of Chriſt in the ſoul, is Chriſt ſpiritually in the ſoul:</hi> viz. in the ſence before ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>The Spirit of Chriſt in the ſoul, doth alwayes act, and bias the ſoul towards Chriſt:</hi> by this means the intrincicall bent, and frame of the heart is toward Chriſt; the Spirit having a moſt ſtrong and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall work upon the will, in anſwer unto that great defection of the will through <hi>Adams</hi> fin, in the Commiſſion of ſin. <hi>That which I do,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul, I allow not.</hi> Rom. 7.15. And in the 19. verſe, <hi>The good I would do, I do not; the evill which I would not do, that I do.</hi> Will you ſee the reaſon of both? why, verſ. 22, 23. <hi>I delight in the Law of God after the inner man; but I ſee another law in my members warring againſt the law of my mind, and bringing me into captivity to the law of ſin, which is in my members.</hi> Sin was his ſickneſſe, his complaint, his captivitie; good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe his deſire, his delight, his endeavour: the ground of both, was the law of God in the inner man, <hi>viz. the Spirit of life by Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Rom. 8.2. This did ſtill <hi>bias</hi> the ſoul contrary to that principle of corruption of nature: So that look how naturall inſtincts do act and work in ſeverall ſubjects here below, as in elements the fire to aſcend upwards, the earth to fall downwards, &amp;c. or in all vegitatives, to yeeld fruit according to its kind whatſoever. Or in all ſenſitives, to forbear that which it knows hurtfull; and to feed upon that which is proper for its particular nouriſhment: <hi>The little kid to ſuck his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers milk, &amp;c.</hi> as the holy Ghoſt termes it, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23.19. Or in ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, to preſerve it ſelf from known evill, and to ſeek after known good. Even ſo an holy ſpirituall inſtinct is in the heart of beleevers to do with delight, that which is holy, juſt, and good, and to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry heedfull of that which is ſinfull, and wicked; and its interruption in both is its ſorrow, its complaint, and its pain (as it were.) It is too true, that the beſt of Gods people are obnoxious unto many diſturbances, and hindrances in the inward man; but it is as true, that theſe are their complaint unto God, and their indeavour for cure. The Spirit in Scripture is compared to anointing oyl, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.27. oyl, we know, hath a naturall property to be uppermoſt, if it be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154500:17"/>put into any liquids, whether they be hot or cold, yet the oyl will alwayes aſcend; and though there might be ſome interruption while you powre water upon the oyl, yet ſtay but a while, and you ſhall ſee it ſettle again, and keep all under it: Juſt ſo the Spirit of Chriſt doth as it were raiſe up the heart above all in the ſoul; and though interruptions may be through violent temptations, and ſtrong paſſions, and corruptions; yet at laſt all will be kept under, and the Spirit of Chriſt will be above all. The needle that is once touched with the load-ſtone, though it may be hindred through the ſtrength of ſome motion, yet its naturall bias is ſtill towards the North, and will ſhake, and tremble untill ſuch time as it ſettles there. Even ſo an heart once touched with Chriſt, is naturally bend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing (I mean in reſpect of its new nature) and acting towards Chriſt, and is never quiet in its obſtructions untill it ſettles in him: as the Mantle of <hi>Elijah</hi> being caſt upon <hi>Eliſha,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 19.19, 20. made him run after the Prophet; even ſo the Spirit of Chriſt being once poured forth upon a man, maketh him ever after to run after Chriſt: And as the ſpirit of <hi>Elijah</hi> did reſt upon <hi>Eliſha,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2.15. even ſo doth the Spirit of Chriſt upon true Chriſtians; which Spirit doth alwaies maintain a continuall warre againſt ſin: <hi>Galat.</hi> 5.17. and at laſt, as <hi>Eſau</hi> is kickt out of the wombe after much ſtriving, and <hi>Jacob</hi> poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſeth it alone; and as after long war between the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and the houſe of <hi>Saul,</hi> yet at laſt the houſe of <hi>Saul</hi> decreaſing, <hi>Saul</hi> is ſlain, and <hi>David</hi> weares the Crown: So ſin dies, and at laſt the Lord Jeſus reigns in the heart, bringing down all ſtrong holds there, and ſetling his own bleſſed and glorious kingdom in the roome thereof.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>The Spirit of Chriſt trades for God with the ſoule, as Chriſt trades for the ſoule with God.</hi> There is a holy trade betweene God and Beleevers, Gods wealth and riches are his glory, he trades with Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers, for that, peace and favour with God is a Beleevers riches, he trades with God; for that, Beleevers have a Factor with God in the heavens, &amp; that is Chriſt; God hath a Factor with Beleevers in earth, that is his Spirit, Chriſt brings it about ſo with God, that all that is in God and from God, his Attributes, his Actions, &amp;c. are accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to, and fall in with a Beleevers peace and benefit in the latter end; So the Spirit brings it ſo about in the ſoule, that the whole ſoule and all that is within it, and proceeds from it, is in a ſweet degree according to, and falling in, with the glory of God. Chriſt hath ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:154500:17"/>away all enmity out of the heart of God toward Beleevers, and the Spirit of Chriſt takes away the enmity that is in the heart of man towards God: Chriſt preſents his blood, and his all ſufficient Sacrifice unto God, and by this hee prevailes with God for man. <hi>We have redemption through his blood,</hi> Epheſ. 1.5. <hi>Wee are made nigh by the blod of Chriſt,</hi> Epheſ. 2.13. And <hi>we have boldneſſe to enter into the holieſt by the blood of Jeſus,</hi> Heb. 10.21. Theſe and many ſuch like places of Scripture holds forth the glorious efficacy of Chriſts blood with God in Beleevers behalfe, and the Spirit of Chriſt alſo prevailes with the ſoul, in, and by the ſame blood. 1. John 1.7. <hi>The blood of Jeſus Chriſt his Son cleanſeth us from all ſin:</hi> Not onely quitteth us, but <hi>clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth us,</hi> Chriſt having offered his blood up unto God. God now judgeth himſelfe ſatisfied, and therefore hath proclaimed it to all the world, That <hi>in him he is well pleaſed,</hi> Matth. 3.17. So now the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit repreſenting unto the ſoule the ſame all-ſufficient Sacrifice of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, the ſoule becomes now reconciled unto God; No actions now from God but of love &amp; kindnes, and that becauſe of the blood of Chriſt; So no actions now from the ſoule delighted in, and own'd towards God, but actions of love and dutie, and thankfullneſſe, and that by vertue of the ſame blood, the love of Chriſt now conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them, becauſe now <hi>they thus judge, that thoſe now that live through the blood of Chriſt, ſhould not now live to themſelves; but unto him that died and gave himſelfe for them,</hi> 2. Cor 5.14, 15. Chriſt hath prevailed with his Father, that he ſhould in all things next unto his own glory, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his people, in as much as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Joſeph, Thou ſhalt be ruler over my houſe, and according unto thy word ſhall all my people be ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, onely in the Throne I will be greater then thee.</hi> Gen. 41.40. Even ſo ſaith God unto his people, <hi>Have ye dominion from Sea to Sea,</hi> Pſalme 72.8. <hi>and concerning the worke of my hands, command ye me,</hi> Iſaiah 45.11. <hi>Onely my glory will I not give to another,</hi> Iſaiah 42.8. And the truth is, God will not be glorified but in the peace and welfare of his people, and never did he ſpeake, thinke, or doe any thing but (next unto his glory) with reference unto them: and all this is accompliſhed through the Lord Jeſus in their behalfe; juſt ſo the Spirit of Chriſt prevaileth ſo with Beleevers, that they ſay concerning themſelves, and all that they have, as <hi>Ahab</hi> ſaid to <hi>Benhadad,</hi> 1. Kin. 20.4. concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his ſilver and gold, &amp;c. <hi>I am thine, and all that I have.</hi> Hence it is that their hearts doe ſo thirſte and pant after Sanctification, in ſo much as Chriſt did long to perfect the worke of their redemption,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154500:18"/>crying out, <hi>That he was ſtraightned till he did accompliſh it,</hi> Luke 12.50. Even ſo a ſpirituall heart cryes out, <hi>Oh that my wayes were ſo directed, that I might keep thy Statutes.</hi> Pſal. 119.151. And the promiſes of Sancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication are ſweet and luſcious unto their hearts, and they do plead ſo pathetically, and cordially the performance of theſe promiſes that concernes their Sanctification, the ſtony heart is their deep com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, and the heart of fleſh their ſtrong deſires; in ſo much that theſe requeſts takes up the very quinteſſence and life of their ſoules in their wraſtling with God; in ſo much as that what ever God de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies them, he ſhall not deny them that: the reaſon of this is, That the Lord Chriſt might be more advanced, both in them and by them; So that as Chriſt trades with God for Beleevers peace, even ſo doth the Spirit of Chriſt trade with them for his praiſe and glory.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>The Spirit of Chriſt doth moſt affect the heart with ſpirituall objects:</hi> things that are ſpirituall do moſt take up the ſoule, the things of heaven, the building not made with hands, the incorruptible crowne, the life that is to come, and all thoſe things that accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate that way, are moſt taking and acceptable, it makes the heart ſubſcribe unto the teſtimony that the Scriptures gives of this world, that all here is vanity, that the world paſſeth away, &amp;c. and that that which is ſpirituall is moſt ſubſtantiall, faith, hope, love, meekneſſe, patience, &amp;c. Theſe are their riches, and their ſubſtances, and thoſe duties that are high, divine and ſpirituall, are moſt ſweet, ſpirituall fellowſhip, ſpirituall language, ſpirituall notions, theſe are moſt choiſe and precious unto the ſoule; hence the Scripture ſaith, <hi>That they minde, or ſavour, or reliſh the things of the Spirit,</hi> Rom. 8.5. And the naturall man cannot diſcerne the things of the Spirit, but the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall man judgeth thereof, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14, 15.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, <hi>The Spirit of Chriſt gives a being unto the word of God in the ſoule:</hi> and this doth ſteare and guide the heart and life, this is ſweeter unto them then the honey or the honey-combe, it maketh them ſet to their ſeale that God is true, that <hi>his word is tried,</hi> Pſal. 18.30. <hi>ſetled in beaven,</hi> Pſal. 119.89. <hi>that God hath magnified his Word above all his Name,</hi> Pſal. 138.2. <hi>That the word of the Lord ſhall ſtand,</hi> Eſai. 40.8. <hi>That heaven and earth ſhall paſſe away before one jot or tittle of his word ſhall faile,</hi> Matth. 5.18. This is ſetled in the heart by the Spirit, and there it frames the heart according to it, and this is called Gods writing his laws in the heart of Beleevers, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10. Hence it comes to paſſe, that <hi>they obey from the heart that forme of doctrine that is delivered unto them,</hi> Rom. 6.17.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154500:18"/>So that <hi>they rejoyce at the word of promiſe, as one that findeth great ſpoiles.</hi> Pſal. 119.162. And they ſtand in awe of the word of threatning, <hi>verſe</hi> 161. and the word of inſtruction, direction, conſolation, repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, from the mouth of God, hath moſt deepe weight and roome in the heart. This is one of the moſt clear, durable, and effectuall evidence of the Spirit of Chriſt; ſo that when many other quallifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations faile, and there is no difference in the ſoules apprehenſion between it ſelfe and the vileſt of ſinners, when little or nothing at all of the fruits of the Spirit appeare, when inſtead of faith, hope, pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, meekneſſe, &amp;c. the ſoule is apprehenſive of nothing but unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, and feare, paſſion, pride, hardneſſe of heart, &amp;c. Yet then the word of free grace, and the promiſe of healing mercy, this ſtayeth and ſupporteth the heart; Now this is differenced from that vain, common pretended dependance that meere formaliſts have of the word of God, in ſuch particulers as theſe.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Beleevers in and through Chriſt waits for the fulfilling of the Word,</hi> in him they expect all to be, <hi>Yea, and Amen;</hi> So that being acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the manifold myſteries of God in Chriſt, through him they expect the performance of all his word; ſo that though fleſh faile, and heart faile; yet God through Chriſt is his portion and help for ever, and this is unto him as good as currant money in his purſe, which anſwers every condition whatſoever: whereas meere forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts in a ſleight, general and confuſed notion of God and Chriſt, very faintly profeſſe faith in the word; but their eyes and their hopes are after carnall and ſecondary ſupports, which failing, their ſpirits faints.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>The whole Word of God hath a proportionable being and power in the hearts of beleevers.</hi> The word of promiſe, of threatning, of terror, of comfort, of command, of prohibition, conſolation, direction, &amp;c. each of theſe hath its proper work upon the heart of Beleevers; ſo that there is a ſweet commenſurable and proportionable influence thereof in the heart, making it to rejoyce with trembling; and to tremble with rejoycing. Every notion of God hath a particular work upon the heart, working up the whole frame of the ſoul unto a ſweet and bleſſed poſture of the inward man. But it is not thus with Formaliſts, they haply may be affected with the word of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and ſometimes terrified with the word of threatning; but the word of direction and inſtruction ſeldome takes hold upon their hearts, they are ſometimes tickled with flaſhy raptures of joy, in a
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:154500:19"/>conceitedneſſe of their intereſt in the promiſes, and again as deeply caſt down with unbelief and deſpair, when a threatning of the word ſeiſeth upon their hearts; but they are not proportionably ballan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with ingenious, conſtant, mutuall, and ſutable affections from every part of the whole Word of God.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>the Word of God is a Beleevers meditation, his ſtudy, and that for obedience and conformity ſake here unto;</hi> inſomuch that it hath an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence throughout his whole courſe of life: Look upon him in his relations, whether maſter, ſervant, husband, wife, father, child, &amp;c. or in his conditions, whether poore or rich, high or low: or in his calling, in buying, ſelling, working, &amp;c. the Word of God runs in his mind, and how he might conform unto that, as may be clearly ſhewed from the Scriptures in many inſtances; but that it would leade into too large a diſcourſe. But now it is not thus with forma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, the Word of God runs not in his thoughts, but his ends, and aimes, (and not the will of God) ſteers him in his whole converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo that we may conclude it an undoubted character of the preſence of the Spirit of Chriſt, <hi>viz.</hi> its giving a being unto the whole Word of God in the ſoul; which is the fifth Teſtimony of the Spirits preſence in the Saints.</p>
            <p>Shall we apply this with reference to the comfort of thoſe, whoſe outward comforts are loſt and gone; is it thus with you? do you find Chriſt in you ſpiritually in the ſence formerly ſpoken of? Do you find your hearts alwayes by a ſing towards Jeſus Chriſt, in reſpect of the bent and frame thereof? do you find the Spirit of Chriſt tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with you for God, as Chriſt with God for you? do you find your hearts affected with ſpirituall objects? hath the whole Word of God a being in your hearts? is it not thus with you in ſome ſweet and precious meaſure? Oh do not deny God in you, I know it is thus with you; lift up then your hanging-down hands, and ſtrengthen your feeble knees; rejoyce, and be exceeding glad, great is your por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in heaven: be not caſt down at your preſent condition, God hath taken away the leſſer teſtimonies of his love, that he may clear it up by greater; and is this your ſorrow? You have heretofore of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered up your ſelves, and your eſtates unto God, he hath accepted of your offering; is this your complaint? He hath taken away his ordinarie and common favours, that you might partake of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarie and ſpeciall grace, and ſhall this grieve you? He hath taken away your ſhels and husks (the creature) that he might feed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:154500:19"/>you with kernels (even himſelf) and is this your dejection? Chear up then you children of the moſt high, ſitting (haply for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) in ſackcloth and aſhes, forget not your conſolation, which ſpeaketh unto you as unto children: <hi>My ſon, deſpiſe not the chaſtening of the Lord, neither faint thou when thou art rebuked of him: for whom the Lord loveth, he chaſteneth, and ſcourgeth every ſon that he receiveth.</hi> Hebr. 12.5, 6. Though you are afflicted, and toſſed up and down, yet <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold now you are the ſons of God, and it doth not yet appear what you ſhall be; but when Chriſt which is your life ſhall appear, then ſhall ye appear with him in glory.</hi> 1 Joh. 3.2. All your preſent troubles extend no farther then your meer carcaſſe; <hi>your vile bodies</hi> which <hi>God ſhall</hi> one day <hi>change, making it like unto the glorious body of Jeſus Christ:</hi> Philip. 3.21. Yet a little while, and <hi>the Lord ſhall wipe away all tears from your eyes,</hi> yea <hi>he that ſhall come, will come, and will not tarry.</hi> In the mean while take theſe directions for your preſent practice, the fruit whereof will be ſweet and comfortable to your ſouls.</p>
            <p>Firſt, take heed of ſinning in the time of your affliction, this will torment more then any thing.</p>
            <p>Secondly, ſtudy not your loſſes, pore not upon your miſerie; little good will come by that, but melancholly and afflicting thoughts.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, ſtudy the ſeverall grounds of comfort, mind your Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolations, it will be a heart-raiſing work.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, obſerve every dayes providence, and the Almighty his carefull proviſion for you; this will heighten your experiences, and fill you with joy.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, be frequent in prayer, and <hi>in nothing be carefull; but in all things let your requeſts be made known unto God in prayer, and ſupplication, with giving of thanks. And the peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding, ſhall preſerve your hearts and minds in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Philip. 4.6, 7.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
